January 30, 1933, Germany. Adolf Hitler is appointed Chancellor of Germany. The regime
Nazis quickly begin to restrict the civil and human rights of Jews and
of other people considered "enemies of the state." It also opens its first field
concentration camp, Dachau, located near Munich. Among the detainees were not only
find Jews and political prisoners, but also thousands of homosexual men,
which are located thanks to public complaints that describe them as “perverse.”
Approximately 100,000 men are arrested and more than 53,000 are released.
condemned. All those who are sent to concentration camps are subjected,
often subjected to brutal torture, making them one of the groups most mistreated by the Nazis.
In addition, they are subjected to human medical experiments and sexual abuse.
Due to widespread homophobia and prejudices of the time, homosexual inmates,
They rarely receive solidarity from other prisoners, generally remaining isolated and without any
power within the prisoner hierarchy. During the Nazi era, between 5,000 and 15,000 men
considered "homosexual offenders" are imprisoned in concentration camps. Of these,
Thousands would die, and those who survived would be scarred for the rest of their lives.
Although homosexuality was illegal in the mid-to-late 20th century,
In the 19th century, gay communities began to emerge and grow in Germany. Likewise, the political conditions
and social movements even allowed public campaigns in favor of decriminalization
of sexual relations between men, calling for the repeal of "Article 175",
which prohibited homosexual relations since 1871.
Before coming to power, Adolf Hitler, leader of the Nazi Party, as well as many other leaders
Fascists, condemned the artistic and scientific development that occurred between 1918 and 1933
during the Weimar Republic. They considered it to be a decadent culture and
degenerate. Part of this condemnation consisted of the rejection of public and open expressions
of sexuality, especially all those related to the homosexual community.
Some prominent Nazis, such as Alfred Rosenberg and Heinrich Himmler,
were clearly homophobic. However, Hitler and other Nazi leaders did not tend to
speak publicly about homosexuality, as they focused, rather, on issues
such as the creation of a Greater German State, the annihilation of the Jews or the economy.
In terms of legal policy, the Nazi Party strongly opposed efforts to decriminalize
sexual relations between men and repeal Article 175. During parliamentary debates,
The Nazis claimed that homosexuality was a crime. Similarly, the Nazis thought
that sexual relations between men were a destructive vice that would lead to
ruin to the German people. Furthermore, the Nazi Party denounced homosexuality, ensuring that it
It was a deviation from normal behavior, which clashed with his belief
on the need to increase the pure "Aryan" population and lead a decent family life.
The Nazis believed that the purpose of sexual relations was reproduction, not reproduction.
pleasure, therefore, they saw homosexuality as a threat to the superiority of the Aryan race.
Thus, they claimed that these relationships should be punished even more severely.
than what was permitted by current German legislation.
However, despite this homophobia, there were recognized homosexuals within the movement.
Nazis. Among them was Ernst Röhm, who defined himself as "same-sex oriented."
Röhm was the leader of the SA, a paramilitary organization associated with the Nazi Party. He also
They were known as the Stormtroopers or the Brownshirts, because of the color of their uniform.
For Ernst Röhm, his sexuality did not conflict with the
Nazi ideology nor compromise his role as leader of the SA.
Röhm claimed that legalizing sexual relations between men did not
meant promoting democratic rights or tolerance,
but rather it was about overthrowing the dominant morality. Likewise,
He wrote that the moralism of some of his fellow Nazis did not seem revolutionary to him.
Röhm's sexual orientation was an open secret within the Nazi Party,
until it became a public scandal in 1931, when a newspaper in
leftist party revealed that Röhm was gay. Despite the controversy,
Hitler defended his loyal aide and long-time friend, remaining at the head of the
SA until 1934. That year, Hitler, under pressure from the high command of the German army,
whose support would be necessary to become President, ordered the SS, directed
by Heinrich Himmler, who murdered not only Röhm, but also 300 of his men,
some of whom were also homosexual. After this murder, the conviction of the
Nazi leadership against homosexuality and gay communities increased considerably.
After coming to power on January 30, 1933, the Nazis attempted to dismantle both culture and
such as the homosexual communities that had developed during the years of the Republic of
Weimar. One of the first measures taken by the Nazis against this community was the closure of bars and
gay meeting places throughout Germany. However, in cities like Berlin and Hamburg,
Some of these establishments were able to remain open until the middle of the decade.
of 1930. Many clandestine meeting places also resisted this repression. However,
Increased police surveillance and Nazi closures led to
it would be much more difficult for gay men to relate to each other.
Likewise, newspapers had been one of the main means of communication of
This community. Therefore, another of the measures adopted by the criminal Nazi regime was the
censorship and elimination of all types of newspapers, magazines and publishing houses related to the world
gay. Similarly, the Nazis ordered the dissolution of all homosexual associations.
However, the repression did not end there. The Nazis also implemented new
Laws and police practices to arrest and detain gay men without trial
from 1933 and early 1934. This was part of a Nazi effort
to reduce crime. Similarly, this fascist regime ordered the police to
arrest people with previous convictions for sexual offenses such as public indecent exposure,
sexual relations with minors and incest. Among these detainees were several homosexuals,
some of whom were imprisoned in the first Nazi concentration camps.
The German Nazi judicial system also included castration in legal practice. Since the late
1933, courts could order compulsory castration of certain sex offenders. However,
However, at least at the beginning of this new law, men arrested under Section
175 could not be castrated without their presumed consent. However, in some cases,
Men imprisoned under this statute could be released early.
if they volunteered to be castrated. One of them was Friedrich-Paul von Groszheim. He
He was one of the 230 homosexuals arrested by the SS in January 1937. Von Groszheim was held
for 10 months in an unheated cell with very little food and no toilets. In 1938, he was arrested
and tortured again. After that, the Nazis released him on the condition that he agreed to be
castrated. Friedrich-Paul agreed and underwent the operation. In 1943, he was arrested for the third time.
This time he was imprisoned as a political prisoner in the Neuengamme concentration camp.
Von Groszheim survived the war and died in 2006 in Hamburg, Germany, at the age of 99.
In the autumn of 1934, Reinhard Heydrich ordered the police in all major cities to
compiled a list of known homosexual persons. These records became known as
the "pink lists", although officially neither the Nazis nor the police called them that.
At the end of 1934, the Gestapo, which was the official political police, raided
gay bars and carried out mass arrests of gay men, most of whom were not
were involved in politics. Many of those accused of homosexuality admitted to acts that did not
were punishable under Article 175, hoping to be released. Instead,
They were mistreated and imprisoned in concentration camps such as Lichtenburg or Dachau.
All these measures were just the beginning of the Nazi campaign against homosexuality.
Up to three major events occurred between 1934 and 1936, which
They provoked a radicalization in the Nazi crusade against homosexuality, carrying out a
most systematic oppression of homosexuals. The first of these acts was the murder of
Ernst Röhm and other SA leaders in June-July 1934. These killings
They prompted a change in the Nazi propaganda strategy against homosexuality. Röhm
and the other SA leaders were killed on Hitler's orders due to a power struggle
at the highest levels of the German government and the Nazi Party. However, after the purge,
Nazi propaganda used Röhm's sexuality as an excuse to justify the murders.
In this way, they took advantage of the prejudices of a large part of the German population against women.
same-sex relationships. The second of these measures took place in
June 1935, when the Nazis revised Section 175 of the German penal code,
which prohibited sexual relations between men. Under the Nazi government,
This statute included a wide range of intimate and sexual behaviors
which were considered crimes. Furthermore, the Nazi revision stipulated that acts
Non-consensual and coercive sexual acts between men could carry a sentence of up to ten years.
of forced labor in prison. This change in the statute allowed the Nazi regime to obtain the
legal tools needed to prosecute and prosecute larger numbers of people.
Finally, in 1936, the leader of the SS and chief of the German police, Heinrich Himmler,
created the Reich Central Office for the Fight against Homosexuality and Abortion. This office
was part of the KRIPO, a criminal police force that worked closely with the
Gestapo. The notoriously homophobic Himmler saw homosexuality and abortion as threats to
German birth rate and therefore a danger to the destiny of the German people.
The Nazi campaign against homosexuality intensified in 1935 and 1936. From that time onwards
At that time, the regime focused on prioritizing the arrest of particular men under
of Article 175. According to the Nazis, it was necessary to consider these individuals as criminals
homosexuals, criminals, and enemies of the state. Himmler believed that pursuing these men was
necessary for the protection, strengthening and proliferation of the German people. For that
reason, he ordered the KRIPO and the Gestapo to rush into carrying out a campaign
against homosexuality. And so they did. These police forces carried out raids,
denunciations and harsh methods of interrogation and torture to locate and arrest anyone
who thought it violated Article 175. In the mid-to-late 1930s,
Police raided bars and other popular gathering places
among homosexuals. Police cordons were established around establishments to,
subsequently interrogate anyone who seemed suspicious. Some men arrested
In the raids they were released if there was no evidence against them. However,
all those whom the police considered guilty of violating Article 175,
were sent directly to a concentration camp.
Police raids were public demonstrations that had a great impact on the
Nazi campaign against homosexuality. Through these controls, the police threatened and
intimidated communities and the individuals within them. Despite this,
The raids were not particularly effective. The main means of locating people
that violated Article 175 was through tips or complaints.
A neighbor, acquaintance, colleague, friend or family member could inform the police of their suspicions.
Many Germans agreed with the Nazi policy on
homosexuality. The complainants referred to these people as "effeminate" beings,
"unmanly" and "perverse." Unlike the raids, the complaints were a
a highly effective tool of repression, resulting in tens of thousands of arrests and convictions.
The Gestapo and KRIPO were engaged in interrogating the men caught in the raids and
denounced. During these interrogations, often physically and psychologically brutal,
The police frequently insisted on obtaining full confessions. Under the
pressure from the harsh torture methods used during interrogation,
Men were forced to name their sexual partners. In this way,
There were more people to arrest and interrogate. Thanks to this system,
The police were able to capture entire networks of gay men.
This group responded to Nazi persecution in different ways and not all took the same
decisions. Not everyone had the same options either. Homosexuals categorized by
The Nazi regime, as Aryans, had many more options than Jews and Roma.
or Sinti. The latter faced persecution, primarily for racial reasons.
Some gay men, especially those who had financial resources,
They could try to hide their sexuality. Some broke off contact with their social circles.
friends or withdrew from the public sphere. Others moved to other cities, to
countryside or even to other countries. Some of them also entered into marriages of convenience.
There were members of this group who took risks and fought against the State.
Nazi for political and personal reasons. Some gay men helped
hiding Jews or joined underground anti-Nazi resistance groups.
This was the case of Willem Arondeus, a gay member of the Dutch resistance, who participated in
an attack on the offices of the Population Registry in Amsterdam on 27 March 1943,
during the German occupation of the Netherlands. His group managed to destroy 800,000
identity documents of Jews and other people wanted by the Nazis,
which accounted for 15% of the total number of records. However, shortly after the attack, his unit
She was betrayed and on April 1, 1943, the Nazis arrested Arondeus. She pleaded guilty to the
charges and took full blame for the coup. Before his execution, Arondeus made sure that the
public opinion knew that he and two other men in the group were homosexual. To this end, he pronounced
the following sentence: "Tell people that homosexuals can be brave!"
Willem Arondeus was subsequently executed on July 1, 1943, at the age of 48.
Not all of the approximately 100,000 men detained during the regime
Nazis under Article 175 suffered the same fate. Normally, after an arrest,
A trial took place before a court. This court acquitted or convicted the accused and
imposed a fixed prison sentence. The conviction rate was approximately 50%.
Most convicts were released after serving their prison sentence.
On rare occasions, the KRIPO or the Gestapo sent a man
directly to a concentration camp for being a "homosexual" offender. Usually,
Although not always, these convicts were sent directly to the
concentration camps for having multiple sentences or other mitigating circumstances.
In this way, between 5,000 and 15,000 people were imprisoned in concentration camps.
because of their sexual orientation. This group of prisoners were often required to wear
a badge with a pink triangle sewn onto the camp uniform. Thus, these badges
allowed SS guards to identify the alleged reasons for imprisonment.
The fact of carrying the pink triangle called special attention, since they were
considered a group of prisoners distinct from the rest. According to many survivor accounts,
Inmates wearing this pink triangle were among the most abused groups in
the camps. SS guards murdered homosexual prisoners out of cruelty or
during sadistic games. There is also evidence that SS officers used these
pink triangles on the prisoners' chests as targets to shoot at "for practice."
By mid-1942, almost all of the 200 homosexual prisoners
of Sachsenhausen were executed. Sometimes these prisoners were
assigned the most arduous and demanding tasks in the field work system. In centers
like Mauthausen and Flossenbürg, it was common practice to make prisoners work
homosexuals to death. Later, this crime was classified as a natural death.
They were often subjected not only to physical abuse but also to sexual abuse. The inmates
With the Pink Triangle, they were raped by the camp guards and their fellow soldiers. In addition,
They were beaten and publicly humiliated. At the Buchenwald concentration camp,
Homosexual prisoners were subjected to experimental treatments for typhus and
They were even subjected to inhuman medical experiments that attempted to change their
sexual orientation through the implantation of a pellet that released testosterone. The majority
of the prisoners died shortly after the experiments. They were also forced to test
opiates and Pervitin. In Sachsenhausen, they were also given experimental treatments.
for phosphorus burns at Sachsenhausen. From November 1942, the commanders
of the concentration camps officially had power
to order the forced castration of the prisoners of the pink triangle.
For fear of being included in this group, these inmates were rejected by their
companions, thus becoming isolated and powerless within the prison hierarchy.
In the same way, they could rarely benefit from the solidarity of other prisoners, whom,
Sometimes they were provided with survival tools such as food and clothing.
Josef Kohout, imprisoned after violating Article 175, was 24 years old when he was
He was arrested in March 1939 after the Christmas card he had sent to his family was intercepted.
lover. After the war he recalled how in Sachsenhausen, where he arrived in January 1940,
Homosexual men were not allowed to have any rights. They were forbidden to speak with
prisoners from other blocks or with inmates who wore another badge, because they believed that
They would try to seduce the other prisoners. Their block was occupied only by homosexuals,
with about 250 men on each wing. At night, it was so cold that a centimeter of ice formed
of ice on the window panes. However, despite these conditions,
Inmates of this sexual orientation were forced to sleep in their nightgowns and with their hands
out of the covers. This was supposed to prevent masturbation.
Several checks were carried out every night. If someone was caught without underwear or
with his hands under the sheets, he was taken outside, several buckets of water were thrown on him
water over him and he was forced to stay outside for an hour in the freezing cold. Just a few
Few people survived this punishment. They were also forbidden to approach
less than five meters from the other blocks. Anyone caught doing so,
He was exposed to being whipped on horseback, receiving at least 15 to 20 lashes.
Josef Kohout survived the war and in 1946 met his life partner,
with whom he remained until 1994, when he died at the age of 79.
In the concentration camps, these prisoners could take advantage of the
the fact of being German speakers to access less onerous jobs, such as those
administrative positions. Similarly, some young and attractive men could obtain
advantages of a sexual relationship with a kapo or an SS guard. However, the situation of
The isolation of homosexual inmates made their survival much more difficult. It is believed
that at least 3,100 to 3,600 Pink Triangle prisoners died in these camps.
Similarly, homosexual prisoners could be imprisoned and persecuted in
concentration camps for reasons other than their sexual orientation. Some were sent to
the camps for being political opponents or Jews. In these cases, their sexuality was generally
a secondary reason for their imprisonment and therefore wore a different badge.
World War II began on September 1, 1939. Although the number of men
detainees under Article 175 continued during the war years, the needs
The war effort caused the Nazi campaign of repression against homosexuality to take a back seat.
Many of those convicted of violating this Article enlisted or were recruited by the
German army. The military needed manpower and, in most cases,
They considered a soldier's sexuality to be of secondary importance. This was the case with
Albrecht Becker, German designer, photographer, and actor who was imprisoned by the Nazi regime
because of his sexual orientation. Towards the end of the war, when the German army needed
more men, it was decided to release Becker to serve on the Eastern Front,
where he fought until 1944. Albrecht Becker was one of
the survivors of the war. He died in 2002 in Hamburg, Germany, at the age of 95.
At the end of the war, the Nazis destroyed a large number of records, including the archive
from the Reich Central Office for the Fight against Homosexuality and Abortion. The experts
It is estimated that approximately 100,000 arrests took place during the Nazi regime due to
Article 175. More than 53,000 ended in convictions. In the spring of 1945, Allied soldiers
They liberated the concentration camps along with their prisoners, including all those
who wore the pink triangle. However, the end of the war and the
The defeat of the Nazi regime did not mean complete liberation for homosexual men,
because not only did they continue to be marginalized in German society, but the relations
Sexual intercourse between men remained illegal in Germany for much of the 20th century.
Many men who were serving sentences for alleged violations of Article
175 remained in prison even after the war. Tens of thousands more were
convicted during the postwar period. Homosexuality was decriminalized
in East Germany in 1968 and the same happened in West Germany in 1969.
However, it was not until the 1990s that the German government recognized these people.
as victims of the Nazi regime. When the government quashed the Article 175 convictions in 2002,
Homosexuals who had suffered at the hands of the Nazis had, for the first time, the right to
monetary compensation from the German government for the injustices perpetrated against them.
Due to the continued prejudice against people's sexual orientation and because of the
application of Article 175 for much of the 20th century, many homosexuals were afraid of
share their testimonies or write their memoirs. We must never forget these men who died
or survived and were scarred until the end of their lives. Their stories and their
suffering should forever remind us of the dangers of discrimination and racism,
and hatred of one another, as history often repeats itself.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to like and subscribe
and click on the notification bell so you don't miss it
our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel